Guide to the American Life Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
American Life collection
1824-1952
MS 748
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.25
(3 boxes, 2 folios)
An artificial collection of correspondence, advertisements, brochures, broadsides, newspapers, magazines, posters, programs, printed material, and miscellanea relating to American life and culture, ca.1824-1952.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Separated Materials
The following materials were removed from the collection: exhibition materials transferred to the Exhibitions Collection (MS 893); "Military education in American Colleges," by Colonel Henry B. Carrinton, transferred to the Carrington Family Papers (MS 130); E. Ingraham Co. materials transferred to the University of Connecticut Library.
Scope and Contents
This collection is made up of miscellaneous manuscript and printed items which, although ephemeral, illuminate in unexpected ways corners of American life. The letters, generally from unidentified writers, reveal something about business methods, education and the life of the times. Farming, mining, land speculation, and the opening up of new territories are some of the subjects discussed in these letters.
Also included are legal and financial documents that record the transfer of offices, the price of land, and the cost of goods and services. Printed matter, usch as land offereings, trade cards, advertisements of various sorts, campaign literature and other ephemera are also included and add to the flavor of the periods covered. Both 19th and 20th century material is included in this collection.
Since the items are arranged by accession in numbered folders, there is no chronological or alphabetical order. Wherever possible, however, the material is grouped by subject. By scanning the subject headings in the register, the researcher can readily locate the topics covered.
Advertising -- United States; Popular culture; United States -- Description and travel; United States -- Social conditions; United States -- Social life and customs; Broadsides -- United States -- 20th Century; Posters
- Inventory
  - Letter from E W Mc from Colorado Springs, Colorado to his "old friend," Charles W. Paynter, Springfield, Ohio describing business opportunities and mining operations in Colorado as well as new gold fields in Cripple Creek. 3 p., 1894 September 5 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - AD appointing Hiram M. Dickinson Deputy Clerk of the Supreme Court of the Territory of Nebraska, signed by J.H.Kellom, Clerk of the Court and by Hiram M. Dickinson, with his oath., 1863 August 8 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Receipt for $5.00 for the repair of a gate. Signed, I.A.Moody., 1852 November 6 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Certificate issued by the Hungarian Fund for $1, stating that On demand one year after the establishment in fact of the INDEPENDENT HUNGARIAN GOVERNMENT, the holder shall be entitled to one dollar payable at the National Treasury… Illus. Issued at New York., 1852 February 2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letter from H.H.Stoddard for the Poultry World quoting prices for advertising and enclosing samples., 1877 October 17 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 2 concluding pages of a lecture in praise of knowledge which brings "disenthrallment" to Africans, Asians and "the downtrodden of Europe;" and on the Manifest Destiny of the U.S. Author unidentified., Undated, n.p. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Two letters from "August" to his cousin discussing national policies and family matters., 1884 October 22, Angel Island, Cal 1895 June 2, Cincinnati, Ohio. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - ALS from a husband to his wife referring to the unexpected death of their son. Tells of going to the fair at Maryville [California] where he meets George Newcomb with a new "wife." The writer, a salesman of "machines," speculates on the actual marital status of the pair., 1858 September 5, San Francisco (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - ADS by D. Lyman giving "my Small Sword which was my faithful Companion during our revolutionary struggle..." to his son, Thomas., 1824 September 13, North Providence (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Religious literature
    - Hymns sung at the Center Church New Haven at the funeral solemnities on occasion of the death of William Henry Harrison, late President of the United States. 4 p., 1841 April 17, New Haven (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - The Morning Star. Boston, American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions, February 5, 1857. 12 p. illus. Description of the building of The Morning Star, a ship to carry missionaries to Micronesia and maintain communication between the islands. Among the first passengers were the Rev. Hiram Bingham, Jr. and his wife. Donations are listed by state. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Davis, George W. The Fall of the Holy City and What it Portends. Los Angeles Christian and Missionary Alliance, 1918? 17 p. (Timely Topics No.3) A religious interpretation of the capture of Jerusalem by the British in December 1917 as the sign of "the restoration of all things." (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - S. Rosalia. Engraving showing the saint surrounded by religious symbols. In the background, an episode from her life. 2 copies., n.p., undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Publishers' advertisements
    - Little and Brown. Proposals for publishing…Speeches, forensic arguments and diplomatic papers of Daniel Webster. Boston 4 p. folder. (2 copies), 1851 February 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Hogan & Thompson. Books published and offered to the Trade. School books, medical, law, bibles, illustrated books and the Rollo Books. 1 p., 1851 March Philadelphia (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Politics and government
    - Republican League of the United States. Under which flag? New York, [1888]. Card comparing wages in an English and an American woolen mill, and protesting "any reduction of the duties that will bring us on a level with…Europe." (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Barnet, John. An Oration delivered at Amenia in the Union Society, July 4, 1812...to celebrate the birth-day of our republic. Poughkeepsie, 1812. 24 p. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Cleveland, Grover. Invitation card to the Executive Mansion, February 6, [1883?]. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Lawson, Thomas W. 2 leaflets attacking Harriman, Morgan and Wall Street. 3 p., 1909, September 7 Boston (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Constitution League. What the United States owes to the Negro vote. London, [ca.1901]. 4 p. An interview with John E. Milholland, chairman, Contitution League. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - The Old Man's Story. An earnest protest against a tyrannical priesthood. [Bucyrus, Ohio, n.d.] 4 p. A protest by a hotel-keeper penalized by a court judgment "for no other reason only he was an 'Infidel'!" (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Industry
    - Hartford and New Haven Rail Road Company. DS announcing a plan to issue 2000 shares of stock in order to extend the road to Springfield. 1843, Apr 13, Hartford. 2 p.; address on verso to Henry White, New Haven. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Ure, Andrew, analytical chemist. Report of the chemical analysis and examination of four samples of iron ore from Mr. Ross, Halifax, Nova Scotia,… London, 1847 Mar 25. 4 p. Concluding that the "proposed company, if well directed, is likely to realize a large fortune, and to pay liberal dividends to the Shareholders." (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Central Railroad Company of New Jersey. Propositions...for the sale of its general mortgage bonds. New York, June 3, 1887. [8] p. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Patented products - Descriptions, advertisements
    - McCambridge & Co. Patent improved train brake. Three signed testimonials dated December 20,1866 and January 10, 1867. 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Harrison Boiler Works. Philadelphia, January 1870. Scale drawings of the Harrison Boiler, 50 horsepower, patented October 4, 1859. Front and side elevations. 1 sheet, torn. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - C.C. Weston's Improved Patent Incubator. Orient Farm and Poultry Yards. Laurel, Maryland, 1877. A printed circular letter describing the workings of the incubator. 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Kendrick, Davis & Co. Lebanon, New Hampshire. Patent dust proof watch-keys. Trade card, illus. n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Resorts, restaurants, travel brochures
    - White Star Line. United States and Royal Mail S.S. Britannic, from Liverpool to New York, September 7, 1882. Saloon passenger list. 4 p. illus. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Mecca Sanitarium, Titusville, Pa. Advertisement for the mineral springs, offering free treatment as well Liniment and its application. Illus. Removed from scrapbook. Partially obscured testimonials on verso. [1892]. 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Southern Pacific. Passenger Department, New Orleans, La.
      - The Old Absinthe House, by Judge L. O'Donnell./ New Orleans, March 26, 1894. 8 p. illus. 2 copies. (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - The French Opera. [New Orleans, 1894].14 p. illus. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - The Yonkers Guide. May, 1899. Issued monthly by the Yonkers businessmen. 28 p. A directory of businesses and services. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - The Crescent City and the New St. Charles. New Orleans, 1908. 32 p. illus. Description of the hotel, sightseeing guide, and schedule for the Mardi Gras. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - The Patriots' Hall. Valley Forge. [4] p. 1909? illus. Fund raising brochure describing the newly built museum and library, and plans for future acquisitions. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Revere House. Breakfast bill of fare. 1 p. illus. [n.p., n.d.]. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Amusements
    - Eden Musee. Programme of Views. American Cinematograph New York, April 1904. [4] p. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Advertisements - miscellaneous
    - The New York Dying and Printing Establishment. New York, 1837. 12 cm. Listing of services. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Elm City Poultry Yards and Pigeon Lofts. Charles H. Loomis, proprietor. New Haven, [ca.1875]. [4] p. illus. Essay on raising "fowls as a pleasure and profit." Description of birds, and prices. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Figurative Chameleon Top. Illustrated directions for spinning the top. 1 p. with 12 figures. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Charles H. Gaus, English and German, Prescription Pharmacy… Albany New York. With a chart of homoeopathic remedies and their use. [Broadside] (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - The Burton Holmes Travelogues. Boston, William W. Westcott, 1926. 6p. illus. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Advertisements--Clocks and watches
    - Nelson H. Brown. Hall clocks and mantel chimes., Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Scope and Contents
      Boston, [n.d.]. [20] p. illus. including an illustration of the Olympia music box.
  - Education--Riverview Academy, Poughkeepsie, N.Y., 1877? (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Catalogue. 37 p. including a program of the course of study, an outline of the ideals of the school, and a listing of the students between 1867 and 1877.
  - Children's literature -- Periodical. THE YOUNG CHRISTIAN SOLDIER. New York, Protestant Episcopal Church. Domestic missions. v.1, no.6, May 1868. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - New York State: 5 announcement cards for a series of programs on American history from Station WGY. April, May 1929. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Advertisements - miscellaneous
    - The oriental base burning hot air furnace, for brick setting. Manufactured by Perry & Co. Oriental Stove Works, Albany, N.Y.,1868. 4p. illus. in red and black. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Doty's mandrake bitters!...C.C. Doty & Co., Proprietors, Bradford, Vt. n.d. 27x12cm. With seven testimonials. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Church finance: The Five Points Mission. New York, 1867. Appeal for funds for the Thanksgiving Dinner for children of the neighborhood. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Politics and government: Fremont, John Charles 1813-1890 Fremont ticket for presidential electors. n.p. [1864]. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Advertisements - miscellaneous
    - H.H.Warner & Co. Warner's Safe Cure: Kidney and Liver, Brights Disease; Urinary Disorders…Rochester, New York. 1883. On obverse colored illustration of the battle of Tippecanoe with the legend, "After once using our 'Tippecanoe' you will use no nostrums nor preparations called 'bitters'. Try 'Tippecanoe' instead." (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Hilles & Culberson, Barnesville, Ohio. Improved ball combination padlock. n.d. 1 p. illus. with description of the working of the new lock. Rights of the patent offered for sale by the American Patent Agency, Cincinnati, Ohio. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Jarvis B. Edson. Edson's Recording steam gauge and alarm. New York, [ca.l893]. 2 p. illus. with testimonial letters. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Wilbur L. Cross, breeder of high class and premium silver duckwing and red pile games. Gurleyville, Connecticut. [n.d.] Trade card. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Advertisements - clocks and watches
    General note
    Transferred to Ingraham Company Collection.
    - Nelson H. Brown. Hall clocks and mantel chimes. Boston, [n.d.]. [20] p. illus. including an illustration of the Olympia music box. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - E.Ingraham Co. Ingraham watches and clocks. Catalogue No.39, 1918-1919. Bristol, Connecticut. 31 p. Illus. Photographs of the plant and office building as well as of watch and clock models, with prices. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - E. Ingraham Co. Ingraham Watches and clocks. Colored supplement to Catalog No. 43, 1928-1929. Bristol, Connecticut. 12 p. illus. Drawings of the plant and of the founders of the company as well as of clocks. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Education
    Transferred to Carrington Family Papers, MS 130, Box 11.
    - Carrington, Colonel Henry B."Military education in American colleges." Reprinted from the Wabash Magazine, March 1870. 15 p. Information on Wabash College, Crawfordsville, Indiana is included on the final leaf of the reprint. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Riverview Academy, Poughkeepsie, N.Y. Catalogue. [1877?] 37 p. including a program of the course of study, an outline of the ideals of the school, and a listing of the students between 1867 and 1877. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Children's literature: Work and Win. An interesting weekly for young America. New York, April 21, 1916. No. 907. Containing a complete story in the Fred Fearnot series. "Fred Fearnot and the rioters; or, backing up the sheriff," by Hal Standish. And other stories. 30 p. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Women: Second Congress of Women, 1874. Circular letter of Invitation. August 11, 1874. 6 p. brochure announcing the Congress to be held in Chicago, October 15-17,1874 and listing the topics to be discussed. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Resorts, restaurants, travel brochures: Topeka and its advantages. Topeka, 1888. 24p. Brochure emphasizing the development of Kansas in the preceding decade. "There is no city in the country which offers more inducements to those who seek a desirable home than the beautiful capital city of Kansas." (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - New York State: Miscellaneous legal and financial documents. 1790-1864. Some are printed forms filled in. Others are fragments. Also complete documents, MS with seals. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - North Carolina: DS (printed form filled in), appointing Hugh W. Tener as Commissioner for the State of North Carolina in and for the State of Pennsylvania. Signed: Thomas Bragg, Governor. 13 October 1856. 1 p. with seal. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Church finance: Mann, Alexander/ TLS to "My dear Mr. Benton" thanking him for his contribution of $100 to the Missions. 1906 Mar 23, Trinity Church, Boston. 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Politics and government
    - U.S. Senate
      - Admission card.Impeachment of the president. Admit the bearer April 3rd 1869. Gallery. George T. Brown, Sergeantat-Arms. 2 copies (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Democratic Party. New York State Convention. Brooklyn, Sept 24, 1896./ Delegate's badge mounted on red ribbon. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Republican National Committee: Have you been fooled? Soak the rich taxes really soak the poor … New York, The Committee, [1936?]. 8 p. illus. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Detroit Free Trade League. Membership form, with spaces for names and reprinting the "Creed" and "Constitution.", undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Jane Addams Chorus. Campaign songs. [Los Angeles, n.d.] 4 p. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - National Recovery Administration. Stamp showing the eagle and the motto "We do our part." (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Amusements
    - Dance invitation. Irving Calico Hop. Mr.----. Yourself and Lady are respectfully invited to attend a Calico Hop to be held at the Mansion House, Mauch Chunk, Pa. on Wednesday evening October 18th, 1871…[Printed on cloth.] (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Publicity brochure. Miss Margaret Mather under the Management of J.M. Hill. [Buffalo, ca.1883] 12 p. illus. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Advertisements
    - Wm. Church, West Haven Ct. Paragon Washing Machine! Patented May 16, 1876 1 sheet, showing a working diagram of the machine. Printed in red and black. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Dr. Bull's Sarsparilla. Two pages on one leaf. Recto: The Capitol at Washington, with a list of the officers of the "Government of the United States, 1853" with an engraving of the capitol. Verso: Opinions of the press and advertising matter for Dr. Bull's Sarsaparilla. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - W.W. Gale & Co. Electrical engineers and contractors. Leaflet with testimonials from New Haven firms., undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Primus and Lovett. Brochure for Kerosene oil pressure stoves, torches, fire pots and lamps. New York, 1910. [12] p. illus. (no.8) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Broadsides (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Sale by order of the Supreme Court of Pennsylvania...Ecton & Perkiomen Copper mine, Montgomery County, Pennsylvania, March 3, 1868. Attached a newspaper notice by auctioneer, James A. Freeman., 1868 January (Box 4)
    - Assignee's Sale. September 22, 1886...titusville, Pennsylvania, 1886 September 6 (Box 4)
      Offering three pieces of property for sale and a building on one of them
    - [Wanted notice] $100.00 reward for William Henry Jackson..absconded night of October 29th with funds from Wells, Fargo & Company, ALbert Lea, Minnesota, 1909 November 1 (Box 4)
    - Municipality of Shuniah, Ontario. Treasurer's Sale of Lands for Taxes.
      Listing of properties with locations, taxes, arears due. Supplement to the Thunder Bay Sentinel
  - Newspapers and magazines (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - New York Herald, #771, 1809 May 27 (Box 4)
      Includes the text of a message to both houses of Congress by James Madison, May 23.
    - Mew York Tribune, 1841 September 25 (Box 4)
      Volume 1, number 2. With a short story by Warner Oliphant, a chapter of Barnaby Rudge, local and foreign political news, and an account of the Antarctic expedition of Captain James Clark Ross.
    - New York Herald, #3619, 1844 February 18 (Box 4)
      Volume X, Number 49. Political news and a substantial number of medical advertisements, both for medicines and doctors' and midwives' services.
    - New Yorker, #96, 1838 January 20 (Box 4)
      Volume IV, number 18. Poems, a chapter of a serial, religious meditations, an article on Chimborazo by Alexander von Humboldt, excerpt of an article from the Edinburgh Review and political news. On page 704 are the words and music for the song, "The Land of Dreams," by Samuel Lover.
    - Ulster County Gazette, 1800 January 4 (Box 4)
      Volume II, number 88.
    - New York Herald, # 5051, 1848 March 21 (Box 4)
  - Automobiles
    - Chrysler corporation. New worlds in engineering…Detroit, Mich., Chrysler corporation, [1940]/89, [7] p. illus. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Marmon Motor Car Company. Marmon Eight 69 Information Book. Indianapolis, Ind., Marmon (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Motor Car Company, 1930. 31 p. illus. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - General Motors. The new La Salle V-8… [n.p., General Motors, 1939] [30] p. illus (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Mineral waters: Oxford Spring Water Depot. New Haven, Conn./ Advertising for Oxford Mineral Water, including leaflets, directions for use, trade cards, and pamphlets attesting to its chemical composition and its use by doctors. One pamphlet titled, "Oxford Spring Water, Nature's Remedy for all Disorders of the Blood…" has the Hebrew word for remedy at the head of title. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Great Britain - Travel memorabilia: Miscellaneous ship journals, menus, programs from the William Graham Sumner Papers, Circa 1908. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Inventions
    - The Pen and the Lever. Washington, E.P. Hudson & Co. v.1, no.5, Jan 30, 1856 [Periodical. Uncut pages] (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Whitworth, Joseph
      - On the advantages and economy of maintaining a high degree of cleanliness in roads and streets; with an account of the construction and operation of the street-sweeping machine. Manchester, John Harrison and Son. 39 p. illus. (Excerpt minutes of proceedings of the Institution of Civil Engineers.), 1853. (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Smith, William Harrold
      - Patent hermetic process of preserving wood in contact with earth. Chicago, Tribune Company, 1868. 16 p. illus. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Inventor's Guide and Advertiser. Washington, Clayton and Hervey [Periodical], 1856 May 8 (Box 4)
    Volume 1, Number 1, 8 pages uncut
  - "From Clement & Bloodgood, dealers in Dry Goods/ Groceries, hardward and house furnishing goods. Broadway, Flushing, L.I.",[Broadside. Possibly intended as a sheet of wrapping paper.], undated (Box 4)
  - "Questions on geography." [n.p., H.A. Salisbury, Printer, n.d.][Broadside] A catechism on geography concluding with a series of questions on the Erie Canal, and a poem on the Sabbath School. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - The Subway Sun. New York (City), Interborough Rapid Transit Co.[Broadside], 1920 October (Box 4)
    Volume 3, Number 38. Contains an excerpt from the World, Sept. 26, 1920 arguing that the five cent fare is too low.
  - Held, John A., Jr., 1889-1958. Total Eclipse of the Sun, Wednesday, August 31, 1932. New Haven, The new haven Railroad, [1932]. Poster [lithographed] in red, blue, yellow and white. 105x71 cm. 2 copies. removed from the David Peck Todd Papers, Mss 496B. (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - Sports: Alexander, Fred B. How to play lawn tennis. New York, American Sports Publishing Company, 1914. 49 p. illus. (Spalding's Athletic Library. Group IV No.157) (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Trade cards
    - Benham & Whitney. Importers and dealers in Hardware... New York. 2 copies (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Crocker, Hall & Stow. Fancy goods... New York. 2 copies (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Phelps, Ralph (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Resorts, restaurants, travel brochures: Munnatawket House, Fisher's Island, N.Y. With engraving of the house. 1 p. leaflet. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Advertisements
    - International Radio Telegraph Company. X-Ray Division. The International Auto-Ray Dental Unit. [Pittsburgh, 1919.] 8 p. illus. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Brooks Brothers. A chronicle recording one hundred twenty-five years … 1818-1943. New York, Brooks Brothers, 1943. 61 p. illus. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - "Enlightenment through exposure. Televisions's role as a mature instrument for the Public good," reprinted from Television Magazine, January 1952. 11 p. illus. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Education -- catalogue: Select Classical School, Morristown, N.J. Wilbert W. Perry, Principal. Prospectus, 1872-1873. 4 p. With a testimonial from Noah Porter, President of Yale College, June 17, 1872. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Politics and government -- Campaign literature, 1872: For president, 1872, Geo. Francis Train. Equal justice to all. Favors to Friends alone... New York, J.W. Nichols, [1872]. With photograph pasted on. (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Amusements
    - "See the real German Battle Plane just at it was in the war... [Coral Gables, Fla., ca. 1920] [Advertising card, 3 copies] (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Bootlegger and speakeasy cards for establishments in New York and Boston, ca. 1930-1933. 8 cards. (Box 1, Folder 11)